Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Weiner, Jean, 1975 March 2, March 28, and April 11 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 13a-b, 135, 136a-b, 137, Box 69, Reel 212a, Box 70, Reel 212b - 212f, Box 71, Reel 212g, Box 1, Folder 90)
    While Weiner does not specify to which union she belonged (likely the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union), she describes her union activity in great detail. She recounts the benefits to working in a union shop and a strike in which she participated. She describes in great detail the chairwoman of her local, whom she describes as well-educated, radical, and a Socialist. She discusses deciding to take a vacation from work as she had enough money to do so and spending the summer with her mother and siblings in Huntington, Connecticut; she and her sister flirting with young men in front of a country store near their camp; and meeting her husband through one of these men. Other topics include the family's more secular life in the US; the Jewish street gang, The Little Augies; life in Jewish neighborhoods in New York City; and pride in her ability to work so that her youngest brother and sister were able to graduate high school and attend college.
    Transcript, index, and summary are available for this interview.
    Women labor union members -- New York (State) -- New York
  - Weinstein, Helen Taub, 1974 May 1 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 65, Box 71, Reel 213a - 213b, Box 1, Folder 91)
    Helen Taub Weinstein was born on July 26, 1897 in Russia. Her family moved outside of Krakow in the Polish region of Austria-Hungary when she was young. She married in 1920 and had three children, one of whom died in World War II.
    This interview was conducted by Suzanne Michel at the Bialystoker Home for the Aged in Manhattan, New York on May 1, 1974. The interviewer and location are unknown. The interview covers Helen Taub Weinstein's childhood in Austria-Hungary; her family's immigration to the United States (US); her family's religious beliefs; her encounters with anti-Semitism in Austria-Hungary and the US; and her personal life. Weinstein describes her childhood outside of Krakow and the resort her parents owned there. She describes Franz Joseph I's lenient attitude towards the Jewish population, in opposition to the majority of the population of Austria-Hungary. She recounts her family's decision to emigrate due to rising anti-Semitism in 1911 or 1912. She discusses the family's resort in Monticello, New York and her work there. She recalls teaching Polish at the school in Monticello and being paid in fruit and vegetables as she did not have a teaching license. She discusses the difference in religious observance between her parents' generation and her own and the anti-Semitism her children faced in school in Queens and Long Island. She describes the loneliness she feels as an older person isolated from her family and the devastation she felt over the death of her oldest son during World War II.
    Catskill Mountains (N.Y.) |v Anecdotes.
  - Williams, Ellen, 1975 October 23, November 12, and December 3 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 223, 233a-b, Box 71, Reel 214a - 214b, Box 72, Reel 214c - 214f)
    Ellen Williams was born on April 30, 1938 in Darliston, Jamaica. She was one of nine children. Her father was a coachman and a farmer and her mother managed the household. Williams attended school in Jamaica up to the sixth standard in the British education system. She immigrated to the United States on June 17, 1947 and lived with her cousin at 68 West 117th Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She married in 1948 and lived on 120th Street in Harlem. She later moved to Morningside Avenue in the Morningside Heights neighborhood of Manhattan and to the Bronx, where she resided at the time of the interview. She worked as a baby nurse for various families in New York City and as a nurse's aide in the Jewish Home and Hospital for the Aged in the Upper West Side neighborhood of Manhattan. She joined Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in 1963 or 1964. She was a member of the West Indian and American Friendly Society and St. John's Lodge in New York City.
    This interview was conducted by Sasha Silverstein at the offices of Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in Manhattan, New York on October 23, November 12, and December 3, 1975. This interview covers Ellen Williams' childhood in Darliston, Jamaica; her immigration to the United States (US); and her life and work as a baby nurse and a nurses' aide in New York, New York. Williams begins by describing her childhood in Jamaica, specifically recalling her father's occupation as a coachman in Kingston; the perception of this job as prestigious due to the wages and uniforms; and his occupation later as a pimento and coffee farmer in Darliston. She recalls that despite the racial segregation in the schools and churches, children were generally friendly with one another. She describes working as a baby nurse for a family in Jamaica, noting that they treated her like family; deferred to her on matters regarding their children; and introduced her to politicians and other friends of theirs. She discusses the differences between life in the city and in the country; the different roles of men and women in both the household and society; the finances of her household; Catholic traditions, including holiday services and the role of godparents; and other secular traditions, particularly birthdays and festivals.
    Williams explains that she immigrated to the US at the behest of her cousin and recalls the sponsorship and monetary requirements for her immigration in June 1947. Her initial impression of New York City was that it was filled with trees and well-dressed people. She explains that while her cousins helped her to acclimate to life in New York, she had difficulty adapting to the winter weather. She describes working as a baby nurse for various families in New York City, recalling that after her marriage in 1948, she only took jobs that did not require her to live with her employers. She describes her work and training as a nurse's aide at the Jewish Home and Hospital for the Aged in the Upper West Side neighborhood of Manhattan. Williams recalls joining Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in 1963 or 1964 and notes that despite her initial skepticism of its benefits, the union gave hospital workers greater job security and wage increases. Other topics include the differences between her work as a baby nurse and nurse's aide; her siblings' education, careers, and families; her husband's occupation and family; her interactions with and impressions of union leaders, particularly Doris Turner and Leon Davis; her involvement in the West Indian and American Friendly Society and St. John's Lodge; and her visits to Jamaica to see her family.
    Jamaicans |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union (New York, N.Y.)